Puerto Rican Oral History Project records 1976.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Larregui, Dick, 1974 September 11; 1976.001.032
  Born in Downtown Brooklyn in 1930, Dick Larregui was one of seven children. In his time from grammar through high schools, Larregui worked at several part-time jobs in his neighborhood. In the United States Army from 1951 to 1953, he served in Kentucky, Texas, and Alaska. In the late 1950s, he went to work in the Brooklyn Navy Yard. As jobs there thinned, he went into management at International Business Machines (IBM) in 1960. He first experienced Puerto Rico as a tourist in 1964, and returned there on IBM business and stayed. He retired in 1993 and was residing in San Juan, Puerto Rico as of 2016.
  In the interview, Dick Larregui speaks on his own experiences of life at school and work within Brooklyn of the 1930s and 1940s, as well as his military stint in the early 1950s and migrating to Puerto Rico in the 1960s. He recalls Jesus Colón's role in the Puerto Rican community and the ethnic distribution of Downtown Brooklyn during wartime. Larregui looks back on the economic and social conditions of the formative time of the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn. He makes some comparisons of the Puerto Rican cultural experience in New York versus that of Puerto Rico. Interview conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Colon, Jesus, 1901-1974; International Business Machines Corporation.; Larregui, Dick, 1930-; New York Naval Shipyard.; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Employees; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico
- Loperena, Felix, 1974 November 22; 1976.001.033
  Felix Loperena was born in Puerto Rico in 1906. He traveled to New York in 1922 aboard a vessel on the Bull steamship line, working as a steward en route. Loperena first arrived in Brooklyn on a Columbia Street dock and lived nearby in an all-Puerto Rican boarding house on Poplar Street and Columbia Heights in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood. He worked in several cardboard box factories along the Brooklyn waterfront over the years, including in the Bush Terminal complex. At the time of the interview in the 1970s, he lived on Manhattan Avenue in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In the interview, Felix Loperena offers his informed account of Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community as a pioneering Puerto Rican in Brooklyn during the 1920s and 1930s, a time when Puerto Ricans were few and far between. He traces the experience of newly arrived Puerto Ricans in the world of labor; including job hunting during the Great Depression of the 1930s. Loperena mentions specific factories which employed Puerto Ricans along with other ethnic groups. He gives a vivid account of discrimination faced by Puerto Ricans from Irish and Italians, and also touches on how the arrival of labor unions may have helped to alleviate prejudice against Puerto Ricans in the workplace. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Loperena, Felix, 1906-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Work environment |z United States
- Maisonette, Jovita, 1974 April 10; 1976.001.034
  Born Jovita Díaz, Jovita Maisonette arrived in Brooklyn in 1924 and resided in the DUMBO neighborhood of Brooklyn for ten years, until she moved to the Bronx neighborhood of Hunts Point. She was a retired factory worker. Taking the name Jovita Robledo Y Díaz later in life, she died in 1983.
  In the interview, Jovita Maisonette describes the ethnic distribution of the Brooklyn neighborhood of DUMBO. She discusses the racial tensions between Puerto Ricans and Italians in DUMBO. Masionette talks about the economic conditions of the Puerto Rican community and the culture of small businesses in DUMBO. Interview in Spanish conducted by Bob Rosado.
  Maisonette, Jovita, 1904-; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO Historic District (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Malabe, Orlando, 1974 June 24; 1976.001.035
  Born in Savana Grande, Puerto Rico in 1919, Orlando Malabé arrived in Brooklyn in 1934. First residing on Bergen Street at Smith Street, he went to work at a luncheonette before he was drafted and served five years during World War II. On a business contract in the early 1950s, Malabé opened and ran a store in Puerto Rico before he and his wife started a shipping and storage company in 1953. Malabe Shipping was based on Bergen Street at Boerum Place in the Boerum Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn, and did not cease operations until 1992. He was a husband and a father of two adult children at the time of this 1974 interview. Orlando Malabé lived in Miami, Florida in the few years before his death in 1991.
  In the interview, Orlando Malabé speaks of some organizations and people who were leading Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community. He refers to some of the most active personalities like Louis Weber and organizations like the International Workers Order (IWO) and La Civica Vanguardia Puertorriqueña, which were popular in the Brooklyn of the late 1930s. Malabé recalls his own personal history in terms of his migration, family connections and support, early jobs, and business enterprises. Interview conducted by Monte Rivera.
  International Workers Order.; Malabe, Orlando, 1919-; Weber, Louis; Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |x Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; Shipyards |z United States
- Marrero, Luis, 1974 June 24; 1976.001.036
  Luis Marrero was born in Aguadilla, Puerto Rico in 1901. He first arrived on the Brooklyn waterfront in 1920 as a merchant marine, after which he was employed at the Domino Sugar refinery and resided on Sands Street. Later, during the 1940s, Marrero worked at maintaining ships and lived on Henry Street in the neighborhood of Brooklyn Heights. He spent 1951 to 1962 in Puerto Rico, after which he returned to Brooklyn permanently.
  In the interview, Luis Marrero discusses in detail Carlos Tapia's significance to Brooklyn's early Puerto Rican community vis-a-vis the status of Tapia's restaurant as a place of socializing, mutual aid and employment. He makes specific comments on Tapia's business activities and his wife "Dona Yuga." Marrero also provides information on the job market during the Great Depression, including work conditions; with specific reference to the Domino Sugar refinery and ship maintenance along Brooklyn's waterfront. Orlando Malabé, a narrator within this collection, referred the interviewers to Marrero and added commentary to this oral history. Interview in Spanish conducted by Monte Rivera.
  American Sugar Refining Company.; Marrero, Luis, 1901-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Sugar factories |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Marti, Anaberta, 1974 August 20; 1976.001.037
  Anaberta Martí came to the United States in 1953, where she lived in New Jersey, the Bronx, and Brooklyn. At the time of the 1974 interview, Mrs. Martí had lived in Brooklyn for twelve years. She had attained a seventh grade-level education. She was the mother of nine children, and a housewife.
  In the interview, Anaberta Martí describes the ethnic distribution of the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Brownsville and East New York during the late 1950s and 1960s. Martí reflects on the economic conditions of the Puerto Rican community, referencing small Puerto Rican businesses in Brooklyn, New York. She discusses the social conditions of Brownsville and East New York and describes the role women play in the Puerto Rican family and community. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Marti, Anaberta, 1915-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Rican women |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Race relations |z United States
- Marti, Nereida, 1974 August 22; 1976.001.038
  Nereida Martí was born in Puerto Rico and moved to Brooklyn, New York in July, 1951 to live with her godmother's daughter. At the time of the 1974 interview, Martí was married and had two children. She lived in different apartments in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood, where she also worked, until 1959, as a sewing machine operator.
  In the interview, Nereida Martí narrates her experiences finding employment and working in sewing factories in Brooklyn, New York while attending night school. The narrator briefly discusses living conditions and recreational activities in the neighborhood of Brooklyn Heights, as well societal changes in there during the 1950s. Interview in English and Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Marti, Nereida, 1934-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Factories |z New York (State); Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Race relations |z United States
- Martinez, Gumercindo, 1974 October 15; 1976.001.039
  Gumercindo Martínez was born in 1935 in Salinas, Puerto Rico. At the age of eighteen, he joined the United States Army and moved to Brooklyn, New York. He came from a modest upbringing, had six siblings, and his father was a sugar chemist at the Aguirre sugar mill in Salinas, Puerto Rico. Martínez was an active community member and politician. He studied at a commercial high school and became an office clerk before starting a career in politics. He occupied the positions of Assistant Administrator of the Board of Elections and Commissioner of the Board of Elections in Brooklyn. At the time of the interview, Martínez was director of the Bronx Model Cities program. He was married to Teodora Martínez, who was also active in political and civic activities.
  In this interview, Gumercindo Martínez briefly narrates his first experiences in Brooklyn, New York, living conditions in 1950s Brooklyn, and his family's economic conditions. He discusses his political career and goes into detail on his accomplishments as part of the Board of Elections and as director of Bronx Model Cities. He focuses his narrative on voter registration campaigns, discrimination in the polls, and the need for Puerto Ricans to be more invested in United States politics while living in the U.S. Martínez also talks about the history of Los Pioneros and their first march to commemorate Antonia Denis. He mentions many Puerto Rican organizations such as the Puerto Rican Democratic Club, the Betances Democratic Club, La Casa Borinquen, El Bello Ideal Puertorriqueño and La Federación de Sociedades Hispanas; although he does not go into detail on any of these. The narrator also talks about his wife, Teodora Martínez, and lists several of her positions and accomplishments in politics. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Denis, Antonia; Martinez, Gumercindo, 1935-; Martinez, Theodora; New York (N.Y.). Board of Elections.; United States. Model Cities Administration.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Demonstration Cities Program (New York, N.Y.); Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Political activity |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York
- Medina, Felipe, 1974 October 16; 1976.001.040
  Born circa 1897, Felipe Medina arrived in Brooklyn in 1920, and had lived in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Downtown Brooklyn for more than fifty-four years when the interview took place in 1974. He was a barber by trade, and he operated and owned a barber shop. He belonged to Jesús Colón's militano group.
  In the interview, Felipe Medina discusses the ethnic distribution of Puerto Ricans in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Downtown Brooklyn. Medina refers to the social conditions of Puerto Ricans in Brooklyn during the 1920s and 1930s. He describes the political movements by the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn, referencing political leaders Carlos Tapia and Jesús Colón. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Colon, Jesus, 1901-1974; Medina, Felipe, 1896-; Tapia, Carlos; Barbers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barbershops |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.
- Melendez, Angel, 1974 November 11; 1976.001.041
  Ángel Meléndez was born in Puerto Rico in 1897. He arrived in New York in 1923, briefly working at the Vanderbilt Hotel in Manhattan. After obtaining a better paying job at pharmaceutical company Pfizer's Flushing Avenue plant, he moved to Brooklyn in 1925. Meléndez was one of the first Puerto Ricans hired at Pfizer - which was located between the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant - and he lived in close proximity to the facility for the next forty-three years; thirty-five of which were spent working there. Meléndez retired in 1960 and eight years later moved to Corona, Queens. He was residing there at the time of the interview in 1974.
  In a brief interview, Ángel Meléndez gives a description of the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn, specifically in the area of Ellery and Hopkins Streets; in close proximity to the Pfizer pharmaceutical plant. He offers a description of the experience of working at Pfizer as one of the first Puerto Ricans hired at the facility. There is also a brief discussion on the social role of community grocery stores known as bodegas in the DUMBO neighborhood of Brooklyn and the advent of Puerto Rican social clubs in the area of the plant - which lies between the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Melendez, Angel, 1897-; Pfizer Inc.; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Melendez, Filomena, 1974 October 19; 1976.001.042
  Filomena Meléndez was born in Puerto Rico and moved to Brooklyn in 1932. She never attended school and didn't know how to read, write, or speak English. At the time of this 1974 interview, Meléndez had lived in Brooklyn for forty-two years, mainly in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn.
  In the interview, Filomena Meléndez describes life in Brooklyn in the 1930s and 1940s as well as the development of Puerto Rican bodegas in the area. She talks about types of radio programs she used to listen to and compares them to radio broadcasting in the 1970s. She describes how she traveled around Brooklyn despite her being illiterate and having a language barrier. Meléndez comments on the cost of life in 1930s Brooklyn as well as the availability of jobs for Puerto Ricans. She compares the Puerto Rican community from the '30s and '40s to the Puerto Rican community at the time of the interview in 1974 and reflects on how the adoption of an American way of life has affected Puerto Rican values. At the end of the interview, the interviewer provides a summary in English on Meléndez's views on the Puerto Rican community in the 1970s. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Melendez, Filomena, 1885-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Literacy |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Language; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century; Radio |z United States |y 20th century; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Mercado, Peter O., 1974 October 23; 1976.001.043
  Peter Mercado arrived in Brooklyn from Puerto Rico at the age of eighteen on April 9, 1928. He was still a resident of the borough when interviewed in 1974. He was a small business owner in the Brooklyn community, formerly running a small storefront print shop at 314 Adams Street.
  Peter Mercado, sixty-five when this interview occurred in 1974, emphasizes his well-informed view of the Puerto Rican community. He discusses his meeting with Carlos Tapia during the 1932 elections. He makes reference to the de Hostos Democratic Club; describing its activities and stating specific areas where Hispanic American votes were sought. Mercado recalls personalities such as politician Vito Marcantonio, businessman Don Parovereret, César Rodriquez, and Marino Rodriquez; both early businessmen in the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn. He also makes reference to Jesus Colón and Gualda Rivera. Interview conducted by John D. Vasquez.
  de Hostos Democratic Club.; Denis, Antonia; Grevi, Santiago; Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954; Mercado, Peter O., 1909-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Business enterprises |x Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Freemasonry |z New York (State) |z New York; Periodicals |x Publishing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Intellectual life; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Montignier, Gilbert, 1974 September 30; 1976.001.044
  Born in Puerto Rico in the 1930s, Gilbert Montignier and his family immigrated to New York City in 1938. From 1949 to 1952, he lived in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the 1974 interview, Montignier was residing in Manhattan and working as a mechanical designer.
  In the interview, Gilbert Montignier speaks about the ethnic distribution of the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn in the mid-twentieth century, as well as the distribution of Puerto Ricans in the South Bronx and New York City as a whole in the early 1970s. He recalls the early 1950s encounters he had with a Williamsburg community leader, Mr. Hernandez, and his encounter with New York politician Vito Marcantonio. In closing, Montignier references the skewed treatment of Puerto Ricans in academics and in the urban economy. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Marcantonio, Vito, 1902-1954; Montignier, Gilbert; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Politicians |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Housing |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Mulero, Mildred, 1974 September 26; 1976.001.045
  Mildred Mulero was born in 1928 and raised in Brooklyn; first in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant and after 1944, in the Williamsburg section. She and her siblings grew up in a traditional, religious Protestant household and later socialized with a diverse group of neighborhood friends. At the time of the interview in 1974, Mulero was working as an educational assistant in a predominantly Puerto Rican New York City public school.
  In the interview, Mildred Mulero recounts growing up in the 1930s and 1940s; recalling the diverse array of businesses, religions, and ethnicities in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Williamsburg neighborhoods of Brooklyn. She describes a traditional religious upbringing, youthful activities, and an ethnically mixed clique of teenage friends and acquaintances in Williamsburg. She recalls the neighborhood developing over the years from German nd Irish to predominantly Puerto Rican. Education, religious, and political leadership is briefly discussed. Spanish-language news media in the Puerto Rican community is also touched on. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Bonilla, Carmelita, 1908-; Mulero, Mildred, 1928-; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Puerto Rican families |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Social conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York Region |x Religion; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Negron, Sophie, 1974 August 27; 1976.001.046
  Sophie Negrón was born in Puerto Rico and moved to the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1926 with her husband and son. She had seven children after moving to Brooklyn, two of whom passed away as infants. Negrón was a housewife while her husband was a factory worker and later a railroad worker.